<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-07-15T21:05:56+00:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Bread Magazine</title><subtitle>Connecting People Through Bread. Online archive of all Bread Magazine content created between 2012 and 2020.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Biological Species of Ancient and Modern Wheats</title><link href="/the-biological-species-of-ancient-and-modern-wheats/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Biological Species of Ancient and Modern Wheats" /><published>2018-12-08T11:34:57+00:00</published><updated>2018-12-08T11:34:57+00:00</updated><id>/the-biological-species-of-ancient-and-modern-wheats</id><content type="html" xml:base="/the-biological-species-of-ancient-and-modern-wheats/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/Bread-Magazine-Vincent_van_Gogh_1853-1890_-_Wheat_Field_with_Crows_1890.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first part of this series about &lt;a href=&quot;https://bread-magazine.com/heirloom-ancient-heritage-and-landrace-grains-are-they-all-the-same/&quot;&gt;heirloom/heritage, ancient, and landrace grains&lt;/a&gt;, we discussed the terminology we use to describe these grains. In this article, we will address the biological dimension of these grains’ evolution and characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may have heard of different sorts of wheat flours, whether these are made out of soft/hard, and red/white wheat. Bread bakers readily get their flours from the marketplace – they buy flours labelled as “bread flour” –, but not all bread flours are made equal. Understanding the specifics of grain classification, particularly that of wheat, will help you make better choices, and will allow you to better explain the differences to your customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wheat-is-a-grass&quot;&gt;Wheat is a grass&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humans have fed on plants, fruits, and animals for thousands of years. Wild plants have been part of its diet long before the agricultural revolution. The grains are the vehicule for the reproduction of these grasses. They contain the genes, the nutrients, and the energy to fuel the grain’s growth into a new generation of plants. And these plants will again produce grains, which will turn into seeds, and the cycle continues on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When hunter gatherers progressively managed to sow, grow, and harvest the grains of some of these wild plants, they picked the sorts that were already thriving on their own, without any human intervention. Slowly, the selection of grains for some of their qualities, properties, and functionalities gave rise to new species of grains. &lt;a href=&quot;https://heritageradionetwork.org/podcast/the-great-civilizations-of-grain/&quot;&gt;Domesticating grains and wheats have been the cornerstone of civilizations&lt;/a&gt; thousands of years ago, and recently, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 21st century, not only have these selections become very complex, they are also acccompanied by &lt;a href=&quot;http://thebreadlab.wsu.edu/&quot;&gt;research at the genetical, biological, and ecological levels&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-families-tribes-and-species-of-grains&quot;&gt;The families, tribes, and species of grains&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of grass classification, we make use of biological taxonomies which include: family, subfamily, tribe, species, and subspecies. These taxonomies serve to classify grasses and grains appropriately. This classification largely depends on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eatthispodcast.com/our-daily-bread-04/&quot;&gt;genetical characteristics of grains and wheats&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/triticum.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Source: Wikimedia Commons&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grass family itself, and as a whole, is called &lt;em&gt;Poaceae&lt;/em&gt; in Latin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The subfamily which mostly interests us for its bread-making quality is called &lt;em&gt;Pooideae&lt;/em&gt; – whereas other subfamilies include other grains such as corn, millet, rice, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From there, we move into the &lt;em&gt;Triticeae&lt;/em&gt; tribe, which contains the many species of bread-making quality grains we’re most familiar with. That’s why all these grains are named first by mentioning their tribe name, &lt;em&gt;“Triticum.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grain species that are part of the &lt;em&gt;Triticeae&lt;/em&gt; tribe include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bread wheat (&lt;em&gt;Triticum aestivum&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Einkorn (&lt;em&gt;Triticum monococcum&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Emmer (&lt;em&gt;Triticum dicoccum&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spelt (&lt;em&gt;Triticum spelta&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Durum (&lt;em&gt;Triticum durum&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Khorasan (&lt;em&gt;Triticum turanicum&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rye (&lt;em&gt;Secale cereale&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Barley (&lt;em&gt;Hordeum vulgare&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only Triticeae grain that doesn’t have any bread-making quality is barley – and rye, depending on whether you’re a rye adept or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barley is included in this tribe because it has evolved alongside its cousins (particularly einkorn and emmer) for thousands of years, both in the wild, and during the early stages of agriculture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a general sense, all &lt;em&gt;Triticum&lt;/em&gt; species are wheats. Therefore, we have wheats, barley, and rye as part of a large tribe in which many characteristics are shared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hardsoft-redwhite-wheats-are-all-triticum-aestivum&quot;&gt;Hard/soft, red/white wheats are all Triticum aestivum&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bread wheat (&lt;em&gt;Triticum aestivum&lt;/em&gt;) is further classified into soft/hard, and white/red categories. And to further complexify things, wheat can be either “spring” or “winter,” depending on when it is sown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s have a closer look at those wheats which are of interest for bread bakers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hard-redwhite-winter-wheat&quot;&gt;Hard red/white winter wheat&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wheat that is sown in fall is called “winter wheat” because the seed germinates right before the ground freezes. The sprouted grain will resume its growth when the weather heats up again in spring, and the grains will be ready for harvesting in July-August. This is the sort of wheat that’s grown in locations which have gentle to quite intense winters (such as Northern Texas, eastern Colorado, Nebraska, and Kansas – and Canada, including colder regions of Quebec).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hard-red-spring-wheat&quot;&gt;Hard red spring wheat&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wheat that is sown in spring is called “spring wheat.” It’s sown in spring, in locations with a long summer, a warmer and dryer weather, or where winters are very cold. The grains are ready for harvesting later in the following fall, in September-October. Places like Dakota, Minnesota, Montana, Alberta, Saskatchewan, and Manitoba are the home of spring wheat. In Quebec, for instance, you’ll find both both spring and winter wheats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hard-white-wheat&quot;&gt;Hard white wheat&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hard white wheat does not possess the gene that gives red wheat its particular color, and its organoleptic profile. As &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;quot;https://amzn.to/2UvziRa&quot;&gt;Jeffrey Hamelman writes in Bread&lt;/a&gt;, the bran of white wheat is, yes, you’ve guessed it, white. So when we mill whole white wheat, we obtain a flour that’s whiter than a bolted or sifted flour made with red wheat, which we’d usually call “white (unbleached) flour.” So the two types of flours that result from different wheats are not to be confused!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hard white wheat is popular is China, where it is used to make noodles. For the purpose of bread making, red wheats are commonly the norm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Globally, there are more than 20,000 known varieties of &lt;em&gt;T. aestivum&lt;/em&gt;. Each year, agronomists, seed breeders, and farmers create new varieties either out of their labs or of their fields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;durum-wheat&quot;&gt;Durum wheat&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Italians have developed many recipes to make bread out of durum wheat, but the main use of this sort of wheat is in pasta production. It contains high levels of protein.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wheat-gluten-strength-vs-quality&quot;&gt;Wheat gluten strength vs. quality&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spring wheats have higher levels of protein than winter wheats (13-15% vs. 11-12%), and are preferred to make bread industrially. The gluten network can be developed to a very strong degree, and the dough can stand the heavy manipulations through machinery. However, dough made with strong gluten may not hold very long when the gluten network starts to desintegrate through the actions of enzymes. It can also break down under intense mixing conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In artisanal, craft baking, winter wheats show a higher quality of gluten. While the gluten network is less strong in winter wheat, it accomodates for better hand manipulation (mixing, shaping), and for long fermentations that progressively destroy the gluten network. With a better gluten quality (rather than strength) dough can be bulk fermented or proofed over long periods of time, and be baked as free standing hearth loaves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;einkorn&quot;&gt;Einkorn&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The German root of the word “einkorn” refers to “one grain,” that is the one grain that grows per spikelet. There are 3 subspecies of &lt;em&gt;Triticum monococcum&lt;/em&gt;, a wild variety (&lt;em&gt;T. monococcum subsp monococcum&lt;/em&gt;), a domesticated one (&lt;em&gt;T. monococcum subsp boeoticum&lt;/em&gt;), and &lt;em&gt;T. urartu&lt;/em&gt;, from which T. aestivum has inherited part of the genome. In other words, bread wheat has some of its origins in einkorn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Einkorn originated in the Fertile Croissant and Caucasus. It was domesticated 10,000 years ago. It is currently grown in Western Europe, and its yield is way lesser than that of bread wheat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/einkorn.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Source: Wikimedia Commons&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;emmer&quot;&gt;Emmer&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emmer (&lt;em&gt;T. turgidum&lt;/em&gt;) was the most “popular” wheat 10,000 to 4,000 years ago. It was cultivated to make flat breads and most probably beer. In 19th century France, it was used to make bread. Currently, it is grown sporadically in Eastern Europe, the Middle East, India, and Ethiopia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/emmer.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Source: Wikimedia Commons&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;spelt&quot;&gt;Spelt&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spelt (&lt;em&gt;T. spelta&lt;/em&gt;) has a genome that’s closer to bread wheat (&lt;em&gt;T. aestivum&lt;/em&gt;) than, say, emmer or einkorn. Archeologists have found spelt grains in exacavations dating from the 6th century BCE. It grows in areas that are not so fertile, in Germany, France, Belgium, and Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Einkorn, emmer and spelt all have their grains covered with a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eatthispodcast.com/our-daily-bread-06/&quot;&gt;hull&lt;/a&gt;. So, dehulling them adds an extra cost and time. These grains are not so popular among large-scale farmers, and because of these extra operations, they sell at a much higher price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/spelt.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Source: Wikimedia Commons&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;khorasan&quot;&gt;Khorasan&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Khorasan (&lt;em&gt;T. turanicum&lt;/em&gt;) is the name of a province in Iran, where the specie originated. The grain has been trademarked as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eatthispodcast.com/our-daily-bread-07/&quot;&gt;Kamut&lt;/a&gt; (supposedly “wheat” in Egyptian) in the United States. It has been grown for the last 40 years, mostly through organic agriculture. Khorasan is similar to durum wheat, contains high levels of proteins (but poor gluten quality), but its grains are much bigger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/kamut.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Source: Wikimedia Commons&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;rye&quot;&gt;Rye&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rye (&lt;em&gt;Secale cereale&lt;/em&gt;) has been used traditionally in many bread-making cultures, including Spain, France, and Germany. Rye contains the proteins need to build gluten (gliadin and glutenin), but because it contains pentosans the gluten network doesn’t develop at all. That’s why it’s tough to make bread with rye flour!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To add up to the challenge, rye contains lots of enzymatic activity. Many bread bakers keep a rye starter, because such a starter will remain very active under difficult conditions. Bread bakers must use acidic and lactic sourdough fermentations to control for the deterioration of starches under enzymatic activity. If you’re into rye bread, the ultimate reference is &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2L3SIIF&quot;&gt;The Rye Baker&lt;/a&gt;, by Stanley Ginsberg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/rye.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Source: Wikimedia Commons&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;further-study&quot;&gt;Further study&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2QLagys&quot;&gt;Dictionnaire universel du pain&lt;/a&gt; is also a complete reference which includes articles on the biology and genetics of grains (great if you can read French.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book &lt;a href=&quot;https://modernistbread.com/&quot;&gt;Modernist Bread&lt;/a&gt; by Nathan Myhrvold and Francisco Migoya covers grains, from biology to agriculture.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>François Thibeault</name></author><category term="Blog" /><category term="ancient" /><category term="barley" /><category term="biology" /><category term="durum" /><category term="einkorn" /><category term="emmer" /><category term="Grain" /><category term="hard" /><category term="heirloom" /><category term="heritage" /><category term="kamut" /><category term="khorasan" /><category term="landrace" /><category term="modern" /><category term="red" /><category term="rye" /><category term="soft" /><category term="spelt" /><category term="spring" /><category term="triticum aeastivum" /><category term="wheat" /><category term="white" /><category term="winter" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Heirloom, Ancient, Heritage, and Landrace Grains: Are They All the Same?</title><link href="/heirloom-ancient-heritage-and-landrace-grains-are-they-all-the-same/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Heirloom, Ancient, Heritage, and Landrace Grains: Are They All the Same?" /><published>2018-11-30T16:44:05+00:00</published><updated>2018-11-30T16:44:05+00:00</updated><id>/heirloom-ancient-heritage-and-landrace-grains-are-they-all-the-same</id><content type="html" xml:base="/heirloom-ancient-heritage-and-landrace-grains-are-they-all-the-same/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/glenn-carstens-peters-112923-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article series on heirloom, ancient, heritage, and landrace grains, we’ll investigate the origins, the usages, the differences, and the bread-making qualities of these grains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lots of bread bakers believe these grains hold very interesting qualities under the current conditions of both grain breeding and farming, and of bread baking. For example, they are praised for their agricultural resilience, their nutritive value, and their flavor profiles. However, there’s a problem: we may assume that heirloom, ancient, heritage, and landrace are synonymous to more “traditional,” “authentic,” “healthy,” and “nutritive” varieties of bread-making cereals. And we oppose them to “modern,” “industrialized,” “hybridized,” and “manipulated” sorts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a need to clarify some of these notions, and to make sure we’re talking about the right things with the right words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, bread bakers are wondering which grains we should focus our attention on, in order to differentiate our products, to innovate, and to better sustain our environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this first part of this series, we begin with an overview of the vocabulary and concepts that serve to distinguish the sorts of grains we have at our disposal. In future articles, we’ll address such topics as the modern agriculture of ancient grains, the biological and genetic characteristics of these grains, their health and nutritional values, what they bring into the local-food movement, and how you can bake bread with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;seeking-for-definitions&quot;&gt;Seeking for definitions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s just start by digging into dictionaries to figure out the common meanings we associate with “heirloom,” “ancient,” “heritage,” and “landrace” notions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;heirloom-and-heritage&quot;&gt;Heirloom and heritage&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a general sense, “heirloom” is “something of special value handed down from one generation to another,” and its specific meaning, it is “a variety of plant that has originated under cultivation and that has survived for several generations usually due to the efforts of private individuals.” (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/heirloom&quot;&gt;Merriam-Webster&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Heirloom” thus “[denotes] a traditional variety of plant or breed of animal which is not associated with large-scale commercial agriculture.” (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/us/heirloom&quot;&gt;Oxford&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Heritage” is pretty close in meaning to “heirloom,” — as a “property that descends to an heir.” It also encompasses traditional values, as it is “something transmitted by or acquired from a predecessor.” (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/heritage&quot;&gt;Merriam-Webster&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is of curiosity here is the fact that heirloom/heritage grains do not remain fixed in time, unchanged. They undergo generations of cultivation and transformation. At each passage, they are transmitted to an heir, and we like to imagine that what is transferred is the same thing as what was passed from one generation to the other in the past. That is simply not the case. Adaptation is part of evolution. Plants evolve by responding to their environment by selecting the traits that will help it survive and reproduce at its best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humans have intervened in many ways in the breeding processes of plants — both at the large-scale commercial agriculture level, and at the more local, small-scale level of permacultural or organic farming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heirloom/heritage grains are as dynamic as the conditions that have affected grain growers for generations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their dynamic properties emerge from the selective and preservation practices farmers have expanded in order to grow and select the best grains out of a given crop, and to plant these seeds as a promise for a better and tastier harvest in the future. There’s resilience embedded in the heirloom/heritage mindset and approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ancient&quot;&gt;Ancient&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Ancient” is, well, that which is not recent, the latest fad, or new, isn’t it? Let’s delve deeper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the one hand, we think of “ancient” grains as “of or relating to a remote period, to a time early in history”. The classical, historical meaning of “ancient” relates to the period that begins with the earliest civilizations and which ends with the fall of the Roman Empire, in the 5&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century CE. (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/ancient&quot;&gt;Merriam-Webster&lt;/a&gt;) It is therefore a period that is no longer in existence, but we have grains that we believe are a testimony of these periods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Einkorn, spelt, and emmer are often labeled as ancient grains. These were sown, grown and harvested by early adopters of agriculture, thousands of years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bakers talk about “ancient” grain as grain that both existed in the &lt;em&gt;past&lt;/em&gt; and that still exist in the &lt;em&gt;present&lt;/em&gt; — because how could these grains be of interest if they couldn’t thrive &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt;? In that sense, “ancient” could simply mean “very old,” that is, which “[has] been in existence for a very long time,” (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/us/ancient&quot;&gt;Oxford&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Ancient” is our means to connect the present with the past. Interestingly, in promoting ancient grains, the “old” can become tomorrow’s “new.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most grains we eat today have ancient origins. We ought to have a second look at whether we’re buying into them for their trendy appeal, or because we know exactly what we’re looking for, and what we’re consuming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;landrace&quot;&gt;Landrace&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In its first occurrence in 1935, in Danish, “landrace” meant “a swine of any of several breeds locally developed in northern Europe. (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/Landrace&quot;&gt;Merriam-Webster&lt;/a&gt;) Generally, it is a “a local cultivar or animal breed that has been improved by traditional agricultural methods.” (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/us/landrace&quot;&gt;Oxford&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The closest translation in French for “landrace” would be &lt;em&gt;“terroir.”&lt;/em&gt; Both words relate to territory to some extent, and take into account local practices and histories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notions of traditional and presumably non-technological (in the modern sense) human interventions at the level of breeding seem to play a role in the manners in which we value landrace, &lt;em&gt;terroir&lt;/em&gt; grains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In France, for example, the &lt;em&gt;Rouge de Bordeaux&lt;/em&gt; is a major example of a landrace wheat that farmer bakers have valued for the last decades. According to them, it shows great flavor profiles, and can produce sustainable yields. (Read &lt;a href=&quot;https://bread-magazine.com/magazines/issue-19&quot;&gt;“The Farmer, the Miller, and the Baker,” in Bread Magazine issue 19&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://bread-magazine.com/magazines/issue-21&quot;&gt;“Elmore Mountain Bread,” in Bread Magazine issue 20&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, these farmer bakers talk about what is called &lt;em&gt;blés de population&lt;/em&gt; in French, which could be translated as “population wheats.” These are various landrace species of wheat (dozens or more) that are sown and grown together in a same field (&lt;em&gt;terroir&lt;/em&gt;). Over consecutive farming seasons, external factors from the environment (soil, weather) and the farming methods (organic, permaculture) will influence the growth, selection, and preservation of certain biological traits over others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Farmer who grow population wheats claim that these show more adaptability to the soil, the environment, are more resistant to changing external factors, develop specific flavor profiles, and result in economically sustainable yields (but yield less than modern wheats).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Annika Michelson, in &lt;a href=&quot;https://bread-magazine.com/magazines/issue-22&quot;&gt;Bread Magazine issue 22&lt;/a&gt; (p. 77), says, “Where monoculture fails, diversity and locally adapted small populations can survive.” She adds, “Landraces were developed throughout millennia, and they are living an open-pollinated life in an open ecosystem. Only by using them will it be possible to produce food in a way that allows humans to thrive.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2SpxJ5A&quot;&gt;Dictionnaire universel du pain&lt;/a&gt;, Ludovic Salvo writes that grain growers up until the 18&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century have mostly relied on the population wheat agricultural methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Roland Feuillas, co-author of &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2RAgaj2&quot;&gt;À la recherche du pain vivant&lt;/a&gt;, population wheats offer denser nutritive value, are more digestible, and rely on farming methods (e.g. organic and permaculture) that are more environmentally sustainable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/wesual-click-431380-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Source: Unsplash&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grains-a-matter-of-time-and-space&quot;&gt;Grains: a matter of time and space&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While “heirloom,” “ancient,” and “heritage” seem to have a greater association with the notion of &lt;em&gt;time&lt;/em&gt;, that of landrace is more specifically linked to notions about &lt;em&gt;space&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;location&lt;/em&gt;. We’d be right in assuming that all of these grains are related to both space and time. In fact, the history of those grains — to be more precise, the &lt;em&gt;story&lt;/em&gt; we tell ourselves about those grains — is rooted in the history of farming practices, and the industrialization of agriculture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Richard Roberts is director of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://kneadingconference.com/heritage-seed-restoration/&quot;&gt;Rare and Ancient Seed Restoration Project at Maine Grain Alliance&lt;/a&gt; He says: “I’m not calling these varieties ‘heirloom,’ because they’re not these old grains that grew 100 years ago. Nobody really knows what these varieties were. We call them ‘heritage’ seeds, and that’s only because they’re from a different location that has a similar climate to that in the Northeast. A lot of people believe that these varieties are these ancient kinds that have different characteristics. They do have different characteristics, not because they’re ancient, but because they’re sourced from a different place.” (From the full interview with &lt;a href=&quot;https://bread-magazine.com/magazines/issue-22&quot;&gt;Richard Roberts in Bread Magazine issue 22&lt;/a&gt;, p. 68.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether we call these grains heirloom or heritage, location and the manners in which these grains have been cultivated over time play a major role. It is the process through time that matters most, rather than trying to single out features that would remain essentially the same regardless of human’s intervention, or environmental conditions. Could such an ahistorical, pristine and pure quality really exist?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where “premodern” and “modern” enter the equation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-premodern-vs-modern-problem&quot;&gt;The premodern vs. modern problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The modern problem, as promoters of an alternative model to industrial agriculture put it, is that “[s]eed breeders changed the seeds from open pollination to closed and started manipulating pollination. They also started to change the seeds’ detailed structures by modifying their genes.” (read the interview with &lt;a href=&quot;https://bread-magazine.com/magazines/issue-22&quot;&gt;Annika Michelson in Bread Magazine issue 22&lt;/a&gt;, p. 75)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From that viewpoint, modern wheats are hybridized and manipulated sorts that no longer retain the properties that they’ve developed naturally over centuries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nathan Myhrvold and Francisco Migoya, authors of &lt;a href=&quot;https://modernistbread.com/&quot;&gt;Modernist Bread&lt;/a&gt;, label as “traditionalists” those who see more value in upholding, and in innovating &lt;em&gt;from within&lt;/em&gt; traditions that have been passed on from one generation of farmer, miller, and baker to the other. From the traditionalist standpoint, the golden age of our inherited practices and values lies in the past. The future can only be improved if we give predominance to what we’ve inherited from the ancients, those that preceded us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contradistinction to traditionalism, they propose a “modernist” approach that seeks to innovate by challenging traditions on the grounds of scientific inquiry and empiricism, and by looking at the future as the place where things will actually be better and improved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They argue that what we consider most of the time as “traditional” or “artisanal” baking methods and techniques are actually the results of inquisitive modernist bakers. They give as example Chad Robertson’s world-renown country loaf, and the ciabatta. While both appeal to our sense of, and our need for tradition, they are modern inventions. The former results from a high hydration dough, for which there is no account in century-old, classical bread recipes. The latter was invented in 1982 by Arnaldo Cavallari, an Italian racing drive who chose to dedicate himself to his family mill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as grains are concerned, the premodern-vs-modern problem translates itself into the mindset and methods of contemporary farming and agriculture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Annika Michelson pointed out, wheat was subjected to modern manipulations that changed its properties beyond what most people could accept as an inheritance of tradition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;which-grains-are-modern-and-which-are-not&quot;&gt;Which grains are modern, and which are not?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heirloom, heritage, landrace, and ancient grains are all, in a way, &lt;em&gt;modern&lt;/em&gt; grains. They are valued from a modern viewpoint, or with the hindsight of modernity, and they are cultivated with innovative, technological means that were not known to farmers even a century ago. Even permaculture is modern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What distinguishes these grains from those we may label as “hybridized,” or “manipulated sorts” is the manners in which humans have engineered wheats that have come to dominate industrial agriculture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story of the agriculture of grains and cereals is something we’ll address in a future post. Nathan Myhrvold and Francisco Migoya write in &lt;a href=&quot;https://modernistbread.com/&quot;&gt;Modernist Bread&lt;/a&gt; (vol. 2, p. 89) that, while hybrid wheats are sterile, are less genetically diverse, and are not yet widely available, “Hybrids work well on a commercial scale because the plants are so genetically similar they grow to the same size and ripen at the same time.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next post, we’ll focus on the biological and genetic characteristics of heirloom, heritage, ancient, and landrace grains, as opposed to industrial sorts. That will allow us to use an even more precise vocabulary to discuss the issues at hand.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>François Thibeault</name></author><category term="Blog" /><category term="ancient" /><category term="einkorn" /><category term="emmer" /><category term="Grain" /><category term="heirloom" /><category term="heritage" /><category term="khorasan" /><category term="landrace" /><category term="spelt" /><category term="wheat" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Tunisian Family’s Love Affair With Bread</title><link href="/a-tunisian-familys-love-affair-with-bread/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Tunisian Family’s Love Affair With Bread" /><published>2018-11-25T10:27:40+00:00</published><updated>2018-11-25T10:27:40+00:00</updated><id>/a-tunisian-familys-love-affair-with-bread</id><content type="html" xml:base="/a-tunisian-familys-love-affair-with-bread/">&lt;p&gt;My late grandfather loved being surrounded by his children and grandchildren, and always attached a great deal of importance to family dinners. During the school holidays, my cousins, my brother and I used to spend weeks at our grandparents’ house. Naziha, my grandmother — a cordon bleu chef — enjoyed preparing tasty and spicy dishes, and would never forget to put &lt;em&gt;khobz&lt;/em&gt; (bread) on the table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“One of the greatest joys of my childhood as a Tunisian,” said Yosra, my older cousin, “was to grab a piece from the hot bread that dad or grandpa had just bought from the bakery, and eat it. It was so tasty and it smelled so good, that I remember myself eating a whole baguette, before getting home.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a family account of Tunisian bread varieties from the perspective of a typical North-African extended family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since my youngest age, I remember eating bread with my cousins, in my grandparents’ house, whenever we were hungry. We would eat many pieces of bread, until we finish a whole baguette, before lunch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bread has always been an essential and valued part of the Tunisian diet. Tunisians have a variety of sauces like mouloukhiya, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cuisinedefarida.com/archives/2012/07/27/24783614.html&quot;&gt;bean sauce&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.geniuskitchen.com/recipe/tunisian-chakchouka-195474&quot;&gt;chakchouka&lt;/a&gt;, that they eat with bread. In fact, bread in Tunisia has a long history dating back over thousands of years. The cultivation of cereals allowed Tunisia, to become a major Mediterranean power, wealthy and prosperous, nicknamed “Rome’s bread basket” during the ancient times. The Tunisian people inherited and developed several varieties of bread since ancient times: &lt;em&gt;tabouna&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;mlawi&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;khobz ghaney&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;khozb zitoun&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;khobz abraj&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/Khobz-Ghaney.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Khobz Ghaney&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The special place of bread in Tunisians’ diet habits is due to economic factors especially poverty. In fact, before the Tunisian independence to the present day, very poor people who can’t buy meat or vegetables, just eat bread and &lt;em&gt;harissa&lt;/em&gt; (a hot chili pepper paste).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, my mother’s family was poor and my grandfather struggled to support his large family of six children. So, he always bought a large quantity of baguettes since bread is very cheap and subsidized by the Tunisian State. Besides, it is very substantial, filling and brings a feeling of fullness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“When I was a child, I used to eat a lot of bread,” said Hayet, my mother, “because that was all what we had to eat, most of the times and it made me skip meals because I was satiate for hours.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why most of Tunisian mothers give their kids sandwiches as snacks so they won’t feel hungry and weak. During our childhood, my brother and I used to take two sandwiches to school, for breaks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“At school, the greatest moment was break time,” said Moucharref, my younger chubby brother, “it was with joy and gluttony that I eat my cheese or tuna sandwich, lovingly prepared by my mother.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even adults, when a bit puckish, make &lt;em&gt;harissa&lt;/em&gt; sandwiches to fill the between-meal gaps. The spicy &lt;em&gt;harissa&lt;/em&gt; with bread is a good mixture to stave off hunger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tabouna&lt;/em&gt; is Tunisians’ favorite and most ancient bread. It’s my grandmother’s specialty, who wakes up at dawn to prepare Tabouna, for breakfast. Tabouna is a traditional bread baked along the walls of a traditional terracotta oven, itself called &lt;em&gt;tabouna&lt;/em&gt;. Made from flour, this bread has a round shape, fairly flattened. &lt;em&gt;Tabouna&lt;/em&gt; is mostly consumed in rural areas of Tunisia, however, during the holy month of Ramadan, most Tunisian people prefer &lt;em&gt;tabouna&lt;/em&gt; to the French baguette. This traditional bread dates from the Carthaginian era and is proved by a terracotta (representing the &lt;em&gt;tabouna&lt;/em&gt; oven) present at the Museum of Carthage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/Tabouna.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tabouna&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tunisians eat straight &lt;em&gt;tabouna&lt;/em&gt; with salads like &lt;a href=&quot;http://globaltableadventure.com/recipe/tunisian-grilled-salad-with-tuna-salata-mishwiyya&quot;&gt;salata mishwiyya&lt;/a&gt; (grilled salad) with tuna, with harissa or with grilled meat. Many traditional fast food restaurants use &lt;em&gt;tabouna&lt;/em&gt; to make sandwiches, which are very popular among Tunisian people. Ilhem, my childhood friend who usually goes on long car trips with her family, to various Tunisian areas, always buys &lt;em&gt;tabouna&lt;/em&gt; from sellers on the road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“When I go on a trip with my family, we always buy &lt;em&gt;tabouna&lt;/em&gt; whenever we’re hungry from sellers on the road,” said Ilhem. “It’s hot, delicious and very substantial.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mlawi&lt;/em&gt; is a delicious kind of crepe or galette, which can be found everywhere in Tunisia. It is a product prepared from fine semolina, flour, a lot of oil (olive or sunflower), warm water and salt. In each city, village or neighborhood, you can find many &lt;em&gt;mlawi&lt;/em&gt; restaurants. This bread went viral among the Tunisian people, because it smells really good, has a fine texture and tastes wonderful (since it contains a lot of oil). People often eat hot &lt;em&gt;mlawi&lt;/em&gt; from the oven, and spread it with &lt;em&gt;harissa&lt;/em&gt;, cheese, tuna or merguez. In rural areas, Tunisians often eat &lt;em&gt;mlawi&lt;/em&gt; with &lt;em&gt;chakchouka&lt;/em&gt;. Besides, &lt;em&gt;mlawi&lt;/em&gt; is students’ and young people’s favorite fast food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Every day, once classes are finished, we would always buy &lt;em&gt;mlawi&lt;/em&gt; with harissa and tuna, and eat it on our way home.” said Yassine, my cousin. “It’s cheap and very delicious. There are generally long queues in &lt;em&gt;mlawi&lt;/em&gt; restaurants, especially during the school year.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/Mlawi-1-300x225.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Mlawi&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Khobz ghaney&lt;/em&gt; is one of the most ancient Tunisian breads and peasants’ favourite bread. My great-grandmother, a peasant woman, always used to cook &lt;em&gt;khobz ghaney&lt;/em&gt; for her meals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“My grandmother always cooked a single type of Tunisian bread: &lt;em&gt;khobz ghaney&lt;/em&gt;,” said Hayet, my mother. “Actually, all peasants eat it along with &lt;em&gt;chakchouka&lt;/em&gt; for their meals.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Khobz ghaney&lt;/em&gt; is prepared with fine semolina, oil, salt, sugar, yeast and warm water. It is thick, smooth and very mellow. It is easily chewed and swallowed, which makes people eat lots of it, without noticing. &lt;em&gt;khobz ghaney&lt;/em&gt; takes its name from the oven in which it is prepared, which is called &lt;em&gt;ghaney&lt;/em&gt;. It’s a terracotta oven, and Tunisians usually put small stones at its bottom. &lt;em&gt;Khobz ghaney&lt;/em&gt; has originated — and is most consumed — in rural areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/Khobz-Ghaney-in-the-terracotta-oven-300x225.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Khobz Ghaney in the terracotta oven&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most loved bread is &lt;em&gt;khobz zitoun&lt;/em&gt;, “olive bread”. &lt;em&gt;Khobz zitoun&lt;/em&gt; is made of basic bread ingredients and has a lot of olives (green and black), onion and dry herbs. These extra ingredients give it a rich and aromatic flavor. Generally, people eat &lt;em&gt;khobz zitoun&lt;/em&gt; during the holy month of Ramadan because it wets the appetite along with salads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My grandmother Naziha always recommends &lt;em&gt;khobz zitoun&lt;/em&gt;. “&lt;em&gt;Khobz zitoun _should always have its place on the table,” she says, “especially during Ramadan when we [Tunisians] most prepare a variety of salads. Kids love _khobz zitoun&lt;/em&gt; too and eat lots of it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From salty bread we move on to &lt;em&gt;khobz abraj&lt;/em&gt; (also called &lt;em&gt;harcha&lt;/em&gt;), which is sweet bread in the form of sandblasted galettes, prepared from medium semolina, water, olive oil, salt, butter and a lot of white sugar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is thick, very coarse and dry. This diamond-shaped bread is very appreciated by Tunisian people, who have it with black coffee or with milk. Some people, to make it sweeter, fill it with dates paste mixed with a pinch of cinnamon, of ground glove, some oil and jam. It is a very traditional bread which was much consumed before, then nowadays due to the advent of the refined pastry industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In my childhood, &lt;em&gt;abraj&lt;/em&gt; was my favorite sweet dish and dessert,” says Amel, my aunt, “since it was almost the only sweet thing to eat, back then.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the advent of French colonizers in 1881, the French baguette was progressively introduced in the Tunisian society. Currently, Tunisian people consume the French baguette subsidized by the Tunisian state, more than any other type of bread. The French baguette, introduced at the colonization era, became a very important item of Tunisians’ food habits. Most bakeries (if not all of them), supermarkets, and grocery store sell the French baguette.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there is still a strong local bread culture. Tunisians still consume traditional bread, not only occasionally but some of them do it regularly because traditional bread is healthier than the French Baguette which contains lots of sugar, salt and can cause many diseases (such as diabetes, high blood pressure).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tharwa Boulifi</name></author><category term="Blog" /><category term="bread" /><category term="culture" /><category term="Diversity" /><category term="Family" /><category term="Flatbread" /><category term="home baking" /><category term="Tradition" /><category term="Tunisia" /><summary type="html">My late grandfather loved being surrounded by his children and grandchildren, and always attached a great deal of importance to family dinners. During the school holidays, my cousins, my brother and I used to spend weeks at our grandparents’ house. Naziha, my grandmother — a cordon bleu chef — enjoyed preparing tasty and spicy dishes, and would never forget to put khobz (bread) on the table.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">From Earth to Hearth: The Art of Connections</title><link href="/taste-for-grain-earth-to-hearth-art-of-connections/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From Earth to Hearth: The Art of Connections" /><published>2018-06-15T09:50:46+00:00</published><updated>2018-06-15T09:50:46+00:00</updated><id>/taste-for-grain-earth-to-hearth-art-of-connections</id><content type="html" xml:base="/taste-for-grain-earth-to-hearth-art-of-connections/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/Carte-postale.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image courtesy of A Taste for Grain&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During my first day at &lt;a href=&quot;http://atasteforgrain.ca/&quot;&gt;A Taste for Grain&lt;/a&gt;, I’d started reflecting deeply about the &lt;a href=&quot;https://bread-magazine.com/a-taste-for-grain-bread-making-lifestyle/&quot;&gt;role and importance that bread-making has in my life&lt;/a&gt;. The second day of the event focused more on professionals than on the general public. I was anticipating great talks about the future of the grain economy, and about the role of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://bread-magazine.com/farmer-miller-baker-grande-suardiere-normandy/&quot;&gt;farmer baker&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-new-grain-economy-in-california&quot;&gt;The new grain economy in California&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sarah Musgrave opened up the discussion with &lt;a href=&quot;http://farmermai.com/&quot;&gt;Mai Nguyen&lt;/a&gt;, the youngest grain grower in California. Inspired by &lt;a href=&quot;http://millersbakehouse.com/&quot;&gt;Dave Miller&lt;/a&gt;”, Mai created a new grain economy that puts sustainability first, while acknowledging the need for sales. An approach that focuses only on sales has major, negative impacts. “One third of the carbon in the atmosphere results from agricultural activities,” Mai says.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to face the heavily subsidized economy of commodity grain, farmers have to reinvest in diversity. Mai became aware of the problem years ago when she opened up grain catalogs only to discover that very few varieties were offered. Knowing that there are more than 145,000 wheat varieties, she set herself on a mission to build “a collaborative effort to revive variety.” She decided to put all her efforts in the resilience of grain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a promoter of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://californiagrains.com/&amp;quot;&quot;&gt;California Grain Campaign&lt;/a&gt;, Mai aims at building accountability and sustainability in the grain economy. She’s also a promoter of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://californiagrains.com/20-by-2020-campaign/&quot;&gt;20% by 2020 Campaign&lt;/a&gt;, whose goal is to make sure that, by 2020, vendors in farmers’ markets in California will use at least 20% of whole-grain ingredients. “We’re building agriculture and infrastructure that will carry us far into the future,” Mai says.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;urban-milling-in-los-angeles&quot;&gt;Urban milling in Los Angeles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nan Kohler, from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gristandtoll.com/&quot;&gt;Grist and Toll&lt;/a&gt; flour mill in Los Angeles, added that this kind of agriculture needs to be built “from the ground up.” For her, that meant building a milling culture in a city. Her major challenge was to build an economy of scale with just spoonfuls of grains, literally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rare and heritage seeds, however resilient or productive they can be, can easily take up to 7 years to yield an acceptable quantity of grain. “The industry has no reference point to help us,” Nan says.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Milling is a craft in and of itself. To differentiate itself from the mass market, millers such as Nan adopt stone-ground milling and whole wheat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For such a small-scale mill business to be successful, Nan believes that it must give priority to grains and flours that are uncommon in the commodity market. That is, whole-grain and heritage wheat can offer an alternative. “We don’t win at a small scale if we reproduce what goes on at a larger scale,” Nan says.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mai added that, “taking care of seeds is a long game, it doesn’t pay in the short term. No one is paying me to do that work—it’s essential! It’s a lineage, and it needs to be done.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;building-soil-through-relationships&quot;&gt;Building soil through relationships&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone, from the farmer to the baker, including the miller and the customer, is engaged in investing in soil, grain, health and economy. “It’s risky being a visionary and a ground breaker. The point is that we should not compare what we do to a model that will be no more relevant in the future,” Nan says.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we realize that we must invest in each other more than ever, we’re giving proper value to farmers and artists whose contributions have been underestimated. Mai says that the point is “to change a food system, and that it’s not about creating a niche.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;so-whats-the-call-to-action&quot;&gt;So, what’s the call-to-action?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nan believes that, “we can take ownership in the process, through education and seeking out local relationships.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mai concludes, “It’s not about you personally, it’s a society that invests in what we care about, in people rather than in for-profit organizations.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;roland-feuillas-building-the-world-one-seed-at-a-time&quot;&gt;Roland Feuillas: building the world one seed at a time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/P1010435-1024x685.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Gwenaëlle Reyt, Roland Feuillas (Les maitres de mon moulin), and Simon Duval-Matte (Les grains du Val). Photo: François Thibeault&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roland Feuillas, from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.farinesdemeule.com/&quot;&gt;Les maitres de mon moulin&lt;/a&gt; (France), expressed deep feelings about the sacredness of Bread, written with a capital “B.” He restored a windmill that was originally built in 1211. From the mill to the oven, from the flour to the loaf of bread, from the wheat grains to the seeds, he is engaged fully and deeply in the revitalization of an earth-to-hearth connection. Roland believes that bakers should possess their own mills, to create breads that are made with 100% natural wheats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“When seeds are modified, Roland says, we lose all the meaning. We become disconnected from the seed itself.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roland set on a journey to find country wheats (“blés de pays”) that have been preserved for generations by farmers in more or less isolated areas. These wheats have been taken care of in the traditional way, that is, they were sown and harvested. They thus have evolved and adapted to their environment, allowing the new seeds to be more resilient, and diversified internally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roland is a former software engineer who faced a major life crisis in his forties. He and his wife, Valérie, converted to baking, farming, and milling to preserve their sanity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From his previous life in IT, Roland kept the principles of open source software close to his heart. He applied that model to seeds, by creating a catalog of heirloom seeds that farmers can exchange freely. Thanks to the efforts of engaged farmers, the law will allow such exchanges of &lt;a href=&quot;https://reporterre.net/L-Europe-reforme-l-agriculture-biologique-a-la-baisse&quot;&gt;heterogeneous seeds in the European Union&lt;/a&gt; by 2021.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a pragmatic visionary, Roland supports a mindful marketing that promotes a product which values country farmers. “Customers pay for the seeds we use, Roland says. A circular economy is much needed.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He created a digital hub where batches of grain are published, sold and bought directly by producers and artisans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He’s an advocate of diversity. “We can apply to large-scale farming the principles of permaculture in which wheat never stands alone in a field. It’ll grow with chick peas, alfalfa, mustard, etc. That kind of polyculture yields less wheat, but it yields more grain overall and is thus more profitable,” Roland says.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chefs and bakers show to the world what can be achieved with wheat, whether it’s grain or flour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“They are like the ‘directors’ of a movie in which wheat has a major role. They create taste, not in any ‘magical’ or ‘illusionary’ ways. They give back meaning to the future. They offer people things that have their own taste, not things that have a taste which doesn’t belong to them,” Roland concludes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>François Thibeault</name></author><category term="Blog" /><category term="A Taste for Grain" /><category term="Mai Nguyen" /><category term="Montr&amp;eacute;al" /><category term="Nan Kohler" /><category term="Roland Feuillas" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to make bread that fits with your lifestyle?</title><link href="/a-taste-for-grain-bread-making-lifestyle/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to make bread that fits with your lifestyle?" /><published>2018-06-14T12:51:41+00:00</published><updated>2018-06-14T12:51:41+00:00</updated><id>/a-taste-for-grain-bread-making-lifestyle</id><content type="html" xml:base="/a-taste-for-grain-bread-making-lifestyle/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://atasteforgrain.ca/&quot;&gt;A Taste for Grain&lt;/a&gt; is an initiative by Marc-André Cyr and Dominique Lalonde. It gathers informed onlookers, amateurs, and professionals around a conversation about grains, taste, flavor, food, bread, beer, and anything in-between that calls for an earth-to-table process involving grains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third edition of the event is an up-levelled version of that of the two previous years, spreading on a two-day conference, gathering, and exhibition, with guests from as far as California and France.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In her conversation with leading artisan bakers from Québec, Genevieve Vezina-Montplaisir, from the independent food-culture magazine &lt;a href=&quot;https://cariboumag.com/&quot;&gt;Caribou&lt;/a&gt;, addressed baking from the perspective of quality of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question is: “How can we — as home or professional bakers — maintain a healthy lifestyle while baking the bread we want?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Amy Halloran, author of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chelseagreen.com/product/the-new-bread-basket/&quot;&gt;The New Bread Basket&lt;/a&gt;, pointed out, the question is probably more about baking the “right” loaf as opposed to the “perfect” loaf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New methods and fermentation techniques — mostly cold fermentation — can have a major, positive impact on both the baker’s lifestyle and her breads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;when-family-enters-the-bread-formula&quot;&gt;When family enters the bread formula&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Martin Falardeau has more than 30 years of baking experience. He shared that his new bakery, the Meunerie Urbaine, meets the challenge of delivering amazing bread while maintaining time and energy for family. His bakery hosts a mill, and the grain that goes into the loaves is milled just-in-time to create flavors that go beyond those that fermentation alone can achieve. (For the curious people out there, you won’t find a website or official Facebook page for the Meunerie Urbaine. You’ll have to visit in Montréal!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Family, as it happens, keeps bakers doing what they love. It also urges us to change how we see bread baking in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mélissa Voghell went digital when she started &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lafilleduboulanger.ca/&quot;&gt;La fille du boulanger&lt;/a&gt;. She created an e-commerce that manages the bread baskets she sells to clients. They log in online, preorder their breads, and Melissa only bakes was has been previously sold. No waste. This fosters a new customer perspective on what it means to eat and buy bread. It’s a new relationship that engages all people who care for soil, grain, flour, bread, and good food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Albert Elbilia, from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mercilavie.co/&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Merci la vie bakery, decided early on that his bakery would serve — rather than harm — his 5-children family. No night shifts. Some of his sourdough breads benefit from 90-hour bulk rise, leaving him time to enjoy every minute he bakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As bakers, we can play a great role in creating new sorts of relationships in our community. That’s because bread has the power to bring us back to that place that’s truly human.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/P1010417.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Seth Gabrielse (Automne Boulangerie), Fabrizia Rollo (Fabrizia) and Ariane Maurice (Patisserie Bicyclette) discussing with Geneviève Vézina-Montplaisir (Magazine Caribou)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;building-a-taste-for-whole-grains&quot;&gt;Building a taste for whole-grains&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a discussion with Amy Halloran, Dawn Woodward, from &lt;a href=&quot;http://evelynscrackers.com/&quot;&gt;Evelyn’s Crackers&lt;/a&gt; in Toronto, shared that customer culture is now evolving toward a greater attention and awareness towards whole grains. As a promoter of organic, stone-ground whole grains, she makes crackers that help her build a taste for whole grains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teaching and education, of both customers and bakers, is a major part of this evolution towards a better understanding of the link between soil, health, and food through whole grains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Author Michel Lambert, who wrote &lt;a href=&quot;https://leseditionsgid.com/catalogsearch/result/?q=michel+lambert&quot;&gt;five volumes about the history of family cooking in Quebec&lt;/a&gt;, says that, “we need to think deeply how we want to bring nature closer to us.” In modernity, agriculture is a means that help humans maintain “control” over nature and culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Balance rather than control should be the key-word. A leap forward would be that we make bread with beans, seeds, and grains the way that the indigenous people that lived where we live 10,000 years ago did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a chef and co-owner of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.automneboulangerie.com/&quot;&gt;Automne Bakery&lt;/a&gt;, Seth Gabrielse shared the idea that, “chefs and bakers have a responsability to introduce products in a format which will attract the public.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not surprisingly, artisans, chefs, and bakers tackle the challenge of selling what they do, and engaging their customers in a conversation that will carry them all together towards a culture of innovation and experimentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taste is as much a matter of culture than of curiosity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Taste for Grain brings that conversation further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bread-magazine.com/taste-for-grain-earth-to-hearth-art-of-connections/&amp;quot;&quot;&gt;Read Part 2 — Reflections from A Taste for Grain 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>François Thibeault</name></author><category term="Blog" /><category term="A Taste for Grain" /><category term="Bread Making" /><category term="Event" /><category term="Le go&amp;ucirc;t du grain" /><category term="Marc-Andr&amp;eacute; Cyr" /><category term="Montr&amp;eacute;al" /><summary type="html">Inspirations gathered from day 1 of &quot;A Taste for Grain,&quot; an event that gathers informed onlookers, amateurs, and professionals around a conversation about grains, taste, flavor, food, bread, beer, etc.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sourdough, Heritage Grains, and a New Book</title><link href="/illebrod-sourdough-interview/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sourdough, Heritage Grains, and a New Book" /><published>2018-05-06T09:00:24+00:00</published><updated>2018-05-06T09:00:24+00:00</updated><id>/illebrod-sourdough-interview</id><content type="html" xml:base="/illebrod-sourdough-interview/">&lt;p&gt;You may not have heard their names, but I bet you have seen the Norwegian
sourdough baking duo’s Instagram account: Casper Andre Lugg and Martin Ivar
Hveem Fjeld run &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/illebrod/&quot;&gt;@illebrod&lt;/a&gt;,
through which, in the past six years, they have inspired over 30,000
followers to improve in the craft of bread making.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, in the form of their bread-making book, &lt;a href=&quot;http://sourdoughbook.com&amp;quot;&quot;&gt;Sourdough&lt;/a&gt;, which was published in the
UK last year, they are bringing their lessons to the international bread making community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/Sourdough-front-cover-Modern-Books-778x10241-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sourdough Bookk&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a long time follower, I have been impressed by the way Casper and Martin
combine heritage grains, high hydration, and long fermentation times to
make sourdough bread with a deliciously open crumb — even at rather high
percentages of wholegrain flour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was excited to ask a few questions about bread, baking and the new
book! Here’s what Martin told me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-making-of-two-bakers&quot;&gt;The Making of Two Bakers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jarkko:&lt;/strong&gt; Tell us a bit about yourself — how
did you get started with bread making and what has kept you hooked since
then?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Martin:&lt;/strong&gt; I started baking sourdough bread about five years
ago, after being introduced to it by Casper. He had just discovered this
magical bread formula, and insisted on me trying as well — he couldn’t
recommend it enough. So I got my first starter from him, baked my first
sourdough loaf, and it was a complete disaster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It looked more like a cannonball than a loaf of bread, and I went back to
making simple yeast rolls and stuff, which I had been doing for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Casper wouldn’t let it go. So, I tried again, and this time it worked.
It didn’t take more than those first OK results to get me hooked. It
was like discovering what bread really was, and there was no returning to
industry bread or even my yeast rolls after that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jarkko&lt;/strong&gt;: Bread has been a shared project between
you and Casper since then: first on the Instagram profile and now also
your new book. Can you tell a bit about your collaboration?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Martin&lt;/strong&gt;: Casper and I have been working very closely
from the beginning, and still today talk about bread on the phone almost
every day — sharing ideas and thoughts and experimenting as a team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Casper had been baking for some months before I got into it, and then we
started the Instagram account together about a year after that, I think. The
book project was very much a continuous team effort: we wrote more or less
everything together via Skype, and we both met up with the photographer for
each photo baking session, baked all the breads together, to the point were
we actually slashed half of the scoring on all the loaves…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bread-magazine.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/illebrod4-325x325.jpg&quot;&gt;Local flour sourdough bread by Illebrød, from their Instagram
feed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, we follow each other’s work very closely as well. But our baking
situations are quite different now. Casper is primarily a home baker, with
small batches to supply his family, first and foremost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, it has become my day job.&lt;a href=&quot;http://illebrod.no&amp;quot;&quot;&gt;Ille Brød&lt;/a&gt; is now a bakery as well —
located in the center of Oslo. I’m very excited about it! This means that
I’m baking larger batches and having to think a little differently about the
process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we still work as a duo and regularly share thoughts on how things can be
done differently, come up with new recipes together and just talk bread all
the time. Neither of us, I think, could imagine a life without baking bread
at this point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jarkko:&lt;/strong&gt; Where does the name, Ille Brød, come from? According to Google Translate, “ille brød” means “bad
bread”…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Martin:&lt;/strong&gt; Haha, yes, that’s the literal translation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in our Norwegian dialect, &lt;em&gt;“ille”&lt;/em&gt; is used in another sense as
well, meaning “very” or “really”, and usually when speaking of something
that’s good, turning it slightly askew — as in “awfully good.” So it’s more
like “very bread”, if that makes any more sense…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started saying &lt;em&gt;ille brød&lt;/em&gt; to each other as a half joke,
and when we used it as the name for our Instagram account, it sort of just
stuck to us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jarkko:&lt;/strong&gt; How would you describe the role Instagram, and
the bread making community there, have played in your bread making
journey?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Martin:&lt;/strong&gt; Instagram has been very important for us, for
inspiration, making contacts and friends, and of course for sharing and
getting feedback. It’s such a great baking community that has formed there,
we’re very thankful to be a part of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-book-on-sourdough-bread&quot;&gt;A Book on Sourdough Bread&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jarkko:&lt;/strong&gt; Your book, &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/2mSeyEH&quot;&gt;Sourdough&lt;/a&gt;, which was originally published in Norwegian in 2015
is now available also in English. We love books and everything about them, so can you tell a bit about how the book deals came to be?Looking back at your Instagram posts from the time, one can see that a global release was at least a dream of yoursalready then…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Martin:&lt;/strong&gt; We were really lucky with both the Norwegian and English book deals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Literally the first publisher we called about the book — actually just to
ask about some deadlines, not even trying to sell the concept — immediately
got excited about the idea, and we’ve had that same editor who
answered the phone ever since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, the publishing house brought one copy of the book to the Frankfurt
book fair. There, when one of the editors at Modern Books/Elwin Street
visited their stand, the book caught his eye, and a deal was made from
there. We’re very happy about getting published in English — and now
even in French!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was definitely a dream from the start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jarkko:&lt;/strong&gt; In a world where there are so many bread making books already, what’s the ‘thing’ yours adds to
the whole? What aspect in it makes you the most proud?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Martin:&lt;/strong&gt; The main outline of this style of baking is inspired by others of course, such as Chad Robertson’s approach, but there
are some differences in our method that we think are key to getting the
loaves we want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We learned this craft from other bakers, just like everyone else, and then
tried to take it a step further. And we’re still working to improve every
day. It never ends, thankfully — that’s what makes it fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what makes us most proud about the book is perhaps the focus on ancient
and heritage grains, a field which still deserves much more attention from
bakers. The book is kind of divided into two main themes: the method on one
hand and introductions to the rich variety of grains on the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;things-that-matter-in-bread&quot;&gt;Things That Matter in Bread&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jarkko:&lt;/strong&gt; You care a lot about grain: local, ancient,
heritage, whole grains… all are mentioned again and again in your
Instagram posts. Why do the grains we use in bread matter?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Martin:&lt;/strong&gt; Taste, sustainability and baking quality are the
main factors for us when choosing flour. The three don’t always appear
together, so you have to have some guiding principles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/illebrod1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Emmer sourdough bread crumb&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early on, we felt that we had the choice between stronger (often industrial
and roller milled) flour that produces very expansive and
impressive breads and weaker flour from stone mills using old grain
varieties that are often harder to work with — but so much more
flavorful and more sustainable both in terms of health, the
environment and biodiversity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would seem like a no brainer when you put it like that, but for a baker,
just as for a cook, appearance is important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, we never took an extreme position, but rather worked on improving the
techniques so that we could use as much as possible of the weaker but (by
all other measures) better flour, without having to compromise much on
volume and spring. Today, we only use stone milled organic flour in all our
breads, from grains that are grown and milled just a couple of kilometers
away. And when baking quality allows it, we stick to ancient and
heritage/landrace grains for the sifted part as well. Which is most of the
time: we haven’t used anything else at the bakery so far!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another important reason for us to use this flour is supporting small scale
farmers and millers who are working uphill in a very industry-dominated
world, competing with big money. It might not be the most available flour,
you might not find it in the supermarket, but in our opinion, it’s
definitely worth seeking out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jarkko:&lt;/strong&gt; How about sourdough? What is it about it that captivates your imagination?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Martin&lt;/strong&gt;: To me, the most captivating and awe-inspiring thing about baking with sourdough is that it’s entirely natural,
in the sense that nature has provided us very directly with everything we need to bake this
amazing bread.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ancient grain varieties first evolved in the wild, the bacteria and
yeast spores were always present, ready to feed on the sugars — we just had
to crush the grain, mix in water and let it sit. That’s how the first
sourdough baker did it 5,000-6,000 years ago. It’s the same to today, and it
will always be available, even without modern industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can’t say the same for bread made with commercial yeast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re not fanatical yeast haters, but it doesn’t have the same depth and
magic about it. And it certainly can’t match the smell and taste of real
sourdough bread made with freshly stone milled flour!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jarkko:&lt;/strong&gt; Finally, with your book now out there for the whole world, what’s next for you in the world of bread?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Martin&lt;/strong&gt;: Opening the new bakery will take up a lot of time.
I’ll do some more courses, and maybe go back to England this summer to do a
course in London — it’s great to meet other passionate sourdough bakers
from all over, sharing thoughts and approaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Otherwise, we’ll just keep baking bread everyday. Eventually we might do
some more writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;h3 id=&quot;martins-tips-for-great-bread&quot;&gt;Martin’s Tips For Great Bread&lt;/h3&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Feed your starter regularly. Preferably, keep it at room
temperature and feed it once or even twice a day. Don’t use it too early
to make a leaven. If you feed with rye and wheat (as we suggest in the
book), it might have a long cycle, so let it sink a little after its
final peak before using it, just to be sure.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Keep the room warm during bulk. In our opinion, it’s better to over
proof a little than ending up with an under-fermented loaf, so try
pushing your boundaries for hydration and fermentation.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;And use the best flour you can find, freshly stone milled and local —
if you can get a hold of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Jarkko Laine</name></author><category term="Interview" /><category term="Baker" /><category term="baking" /><category term="books" /><category term="bread" /><category term="emmer" /><category term="heritage grains" /><category term="illebrod" /><category term="instagram" /><category term="interview" /><category term="local grain economy" /><category term="sourdough" /><summary type="html">An interview with Norwegian sourdough baker and bread-making book author Martin Fjeld from Ille Brød.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bread Magazine Motto</title><link href="/motto/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bread Magazine Motto" /><published>2017-07-29T11:16:40+00:00</published><updated>2017-07-29T11:16:40+00:00</updated><id>/motto</id><content type="html" xml:base="/motto/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/poster-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bread Magazine Motto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do you bake?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you give your heart and mind to?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you believe in?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At BREAD Magazine, we empower people to bake bread that makes a difference. This is our “why,” our core reason for doing what we do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do we achieve this purpose? We foster meaning and connections. What is the testimonial of our commitment and engagement? It’s these words you’re reading. It’s this independant magazine that we publish; the inspiring, entertaining and instructive stories to keep you doing what you love to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We came up with the idea of a credo or motto not long ago when we asked ourselves if we could create a statement that would reflect not only our credo but that of a community of passionate bread makers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we understand it, a community is always locally defined — however dynamic and multifaceted such a definition is constructed. A community starts with people, real, tangible, in-flesh people that relate to each other through meaningful relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond the local, communities exist and perform in a complex, global network of interdependent interactions, organizations, and systems. We can’t avoid the fact that we now live in a globalized society of some sorts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We create our worlds through intimate relationships as much as we build it through our understanding of the wider issues that humanity and nature face. We can change something in this world, for the worst or the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We choose craft baking as a means to improve our connections to each other, to heal hearts, and to make this Earth a better place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Join the movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bake bread.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make a difference.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Blog" /><category term="bread movement" /><category term="Credo" /><category term="manifesto" /><category term="meaning" /><category term="mojo" /><category term="motto" /><summary type="html">Why do you bake? What do you give your heart and mind to? What do you believe in?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Connecting People Through Bread</title><link href="/connecting-people-through-bread/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Connecting People Through Bread" /><published>2017-06-07T09:00:30+00:00</published><updated>2017-06-07T09:00:30+00:00</updated><id>/connecting-people-through-bread</id><content type="html" xml:base="/connecting-people-through-bread/">&lt;p&gt;Bread is unique among foods: an everyday food with a wealth of meaning that goes well beyond its nutritional value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/vespers-550718-325x487.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo: Dirk Hoenes&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether it is a slice of sourdough rye bread served with salmon soup in Helsinki or a pita bread filled with falafel in war-torn Aleppo, bread accompanies most meals around the world — today as it has done throughout recorded history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bread is also a part of our celebrations. Ever since our ancestors learned to master the mysteries of grinding grain and mixing and baking dough, it has not only served to feed us but also to express our hopes, fears, and devotion. The scent of a loaf just out of the oven moves us all, reminding us of some of our fondest memories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But those memories — and the baking skills needed to evoke them — are fading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The industrial revolution turned grain and flour into a commodity, and industrial baking alienated our societies from bread making. We lost touch with the richness of its story, tradition, and meaning. It’s no wonder that consumers today have become susceptible to fear mongering writers who claim that eating wheat is an “extreme sport” akin to ice climbing, mountain boarding, and bungee jumping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baking bread is a way to fight back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When bakers in their home kitchens and craft bakeries take the time to learn about the people who produce the ingredients they use, or think about their place in the long line of bakers, they participate in a peaceful but powerful revolution. A revolution that happens through rebuilding connections that once were commonplace but have since then been lost: between the grain and the loaf, the baker and the person who receives the bread, between generations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we participate in this revolution, we become aware of our interdependent food chains, and we may start to wonder: apart from bread, what else is there in our lives that we have externalized and disconnected ourselves from? By letting bread teach us, we become a part of a global movement in regaining not only our favorite foodstuff but also our bodies and minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In today’s fast-moving and information-laden world, there is no need for more on-the-spot reactions and infuriated social media posts about current events. Instead, we need to put our shoulder to the wheel and make some bread. We need to learn to sit still and let things take their natural course. We need to immerse ourselves in the world around us, to learn and to understand. We need to realize that we need each other, in an interdependent but liberated communion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to connect through bread. &lt;em&gt;And that, we can only do together.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Column" /><category term="connection" /><category term="Credo" /><category term="flour" /><category term="grain-to-bread movement" /><category term="Issue 21" /><category term="milling" /><category term="motto" /><category term="people" /><category term="stone-ground milling" /><summary type="html">A call to empower ourselves and to connect with each other—through bread and baking.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Flour Ambassador Pledge</title><link href="/the-flour-ambassador-pledge/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Flour Ambassador Pledge" /><published>2017-06-07T08:45:55+00:00</published><updated>2017-06-07T08:45:55+00:00</updated><id>/the-flour-ambassador-pledge</id><content type="html" xml:base="/the-flour-ambassador-pledge/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/AmbassadorHiRes.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Flour Ambassador Badge&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dear friends and fans of flour,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I invite you to become Flour Ambassadors. Since you are reading this, I know you are already representing our unnamed country. Loaf by loaf, pie by pie, baking escorts flour back into the good graces of people who are doubting gluten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Please note that I am not being flip about the real challenges people face with bread and wheat. Rather, I am addressing the tendency I see in America to huddle around food fears. I grew up as the food industry, fueled by nutritionism, nudged people to doubt eggs, fat and salt; now these foods are coming back into vogue, as is bread.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I invented this campaign to shine a light on the wonders of fresh stone-ground flour and help build regional grain economies. Like farmers’ markets, mills are the levers that growers need to put something new in the ground. Commodity systems set the stage for farmers, millers, and bakers—determining what seed varieties are grown, how they are sold, and how they are milled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If eaters and bakers want more choices, like alternative grains, heritage grains, and stone milling, we have to support regional systems all the way back to the field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At &lt;a href=&quot;http://kneadingconference.com/&quot;&gt;The Kneading Conference&lt;/a&gt; in Skowhegan (Maine), in July 2016, two hundred people stood up and put their hands over their hearts to proclaim the Flour Ambassador Pledge. Now, I’m inviting you to join the movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together we can build an appetite for—and awareness of—flours that come from somewhere and someone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your Civil Servant in Grains,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Amy Halloran&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.S. Please join me in tagging images with #flourambassador, and @flourambassador on social media. Name your farmer or mill, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;THE FLOUR AMBASSADOR PLEDGE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I do solemnly, happily swear,
that I am going to tell everyone I see
that it’s okay to love flour!
Bread is not poison,
Invisibility is poison.
I will try to make visible
all the labor in bread,
from seed to mill,
from mill to loaf.
Mills are the levers farmers need
to get more interesting grains in the ground,
and on our tables,
and under our butter.
Because butter is terrific and bread is our family tree,
It is time to put the family pictures back in the album,
put the album back on the mantelpiece,
and get acquainted with grains and flour again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Amy Halloran</name></author><category term="Essay" /><category term="ambassador" /><category term="Amy Halloran" /><category term="bread" /><category term="flour" /><category term="Grain" /><category term="Issue 21" /><category term="Kneading Conference" /><category term="milling" /><category term="pledge" /><category term="wheat" /><summary type="html">Writer and flour activist Amy Halloran urges you to become a Flour Ambassador, for your own good and that of many others.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Testing the Mockmill with Andrew Heyn at Elmore Mountain Bread</title><link href="/testing-the-mockmill-with-andrew-heyn-at-elmore-mountain-bread/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Testing the Mockmill with Andrew Heyn at Elmore Mountain Bread" /><published>2017-06-07T08:43:01+00:00</published><updated>2017-06-07T08:43:01+00:00</updated><id>/testing-the-mockmill-with-andrew-heyn-at-elmore-mountain-bread</id><content type="html" xml:base="/testing-the-mockmill-with-andrew-heyn-at-elmore-mountain-bread/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/francois-thibeault-001-Andrew-Heyn-mockmill-wp-e1495312149741.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By two o’clock in the afternoon, Blair Marvin and Andrew Heyn had finished baking bread at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.elmoremountainbread.com/&amp;quot;&quot;&gt;Elmore Mountain Bread&lt;/a&gt; (read the full story in Bread Magazine issue 21). Blair had gone to deliver the loaves to shops and customers. Andrew kept a watchful eye on two 5-kilos (11 lbs) rye loaves slowly baking in the oven. He was baking experimental loaves for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jasperhillfarm.com/cheese-1/&amp;quot;&quot;&gt;Jasper Hill Farm&lt;/a&gt; (Vermont, United States), a farm that ripens a great variety of cheeses. The cheesemaker was going to inoculate the loaves with &lt;em&gt;Penicillium roqueforti&lt;/em&gt;, the fungus needed to make Roquefort cheese. The loaves had to have a very moist crumb and a carbonized crust (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.recette-roquefort.fr/culture-papillon/le-secret-du-penicillium-roqueforti-papillon/&amp;quot;&quot;&gt;read more&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the bread baked in the oven, Andrew and I were talking about milling and fresh flour. I asked him how home bakers could start milling their own flour, and what they needed to know. Andrew had just received a brand new Mockmill (built by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wolfgangmock.com/en/&quot;&gt;Wolfgang Mock&lt;/a&gt;) which he had not yet pulled out of its box. We decided to give it a try and to record our observations as we examined the equipment and tested it with some grain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/francois-thibeault-034-Andrew-Heyn-rye-penicillium-roqueforti-wp.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A five-kilo rye loaf that will be inoculated with Penicillium roqueforti&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;installing-the-mockmill&quot;&gt;Installing the Mockmill&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Mockmill is a mill attachment that fits on a stand mixer (Kitchen Aid, Electrolux, or Kenmore). It can be easily mounted and dismounted, or left on the mixer to save storing space. Its parts are also quick to disassemble for maintenance and cleaning purposes. A six-year-old child can do it—ask Andrew and Blair’s son!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mockmill’s millstones are made of corundum, a crystalline form of aluminum oxide, Al2O3, that can be either extracted from nature or synthesized. It is a very hard mineral that is bound together using a binding agent—in domestic mills, usually epoxy or ceramic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Examining the mill, Andrew noticed that the corundum millstones did not have an excess of the binding agent, which he referred to as “glue.” He commented that some grinding stones from other brands have more binding agent and less corundum, which impacts the milling effect of the millstones negatively. The Mockmill stones carried a lot of mineral and were bonded with ceramic—a more neutral binding agent than epoxy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dressing of the Mockmill’s stones (running stone and bed) consists of furrows in a spiral pattern. The millstones’ diameter is less than two inches, and there are no lands (carvings perpendicular to the furrows), which stones in much larger mills have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;characteristics-and-adjustment&quot;&gt;Characteristics and Adjustment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Mockmill’s website, the mill is “working at speed of only 220 revolutions per minute, it ensures that the grain and flour do not get hot during the milling process, preserving optimal flavor and nutritional benefits.” The stand mixer should be set to its highest speed, and throughput is said to be 2 oz (28.35 g) per minute (1 kilo or 2.20 lb of grain would take 35 minutes to mill).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As suggested in the manual, we first set the grind level to coarse. Then, while milling grain, we adjusted the dial until the flour was fine enough. When grain falls between the stones, it exerts a pressure against them, creating a ball bearings effect between the rotor (running stone) and stator (bed) stones. This is why bringing the stones progressively nearer to each other when the grain has already entered the mill yields a finer flour than trying to get fine flour by setting the grind level at its finest level from the start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding the mixer’s speed, the flour was correct at medium speed, but there were still many grainy and sandy particles in it. Running the mixer at its highest speed delivered the best flour, but the motor was working hard. However, with some practice, it is possible to obtain a fine flour at the slowest speed (thus keeping loudness at its minimum).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-test&quot;&gt;The Test&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/francois-thibeault-003-Andrew-Heyn-mockmill-wp.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Mockmill's hopper filled with Vermont Redeemer wheat&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our test, we milled 500 g (18 oz) of grains in about 10 minutes, without interruption. We set the mill at the finest grind level that we could, which meant going beyond the smallest dot on the adjustment dial. The instructions explained that each Mockmill has its specificities and that the adjustment needs to be done on an individual basis, even if that means setting the dial beyond the marks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seeing and smelling the resulting flour, Andrew commented: “It smells like fresh flour to me! The bran is ground up, and it’s fine. The particle size is good for whole-wheat bread.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Milling continuously at the highest speed and the finest grind level had an impact on the millstones’ temperature, which increased, and on the quality of the flour, which became progressively more sandy and grainy. Andrew explained that this kind of texture was a sign that the endosperm was not being milled thoroughly. At that point, setting the adjustment dial back to a slightly coarser grind, or taking a break would have improved the results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding the milling temperature, Andrew said that milling colder grains could help to maintain a cooler flour temperature. Milling frozen grain straight out of the freezer, however, could create condensation in the mill and create a film (glaze) on the millstones. Grains kept in the refrigerator may not create as much condensation. So, dry, cold grain is the best solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/francois-thibeault-002-Andrew-Heyn-mockmill-wp.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Fresh stone-ground flour out of the Mockmill&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sifting-and-extraction-rate&quot;&gt;Sifting and Extraction Rate&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wolfgang Mock, the creator of Mockmill, promotes whole-grain flour. And sifting freshly milled flour could be a blasphemy for some. But at Elmore Mountain Bread, whole-wheat flour and bread only account for a small proportion of what Blair and Andrew bake. Even though they try to educate their customers’ tastes with a wide variety of ferments, grains, and types of bread, sifted flour (which is not the same as white flour) remains their core ingredient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mills that Andrew builds use a boxlike sifter made with different types of screens. The gage of the finest screen is 80 threads per inch (openings are 0.0070 inch or 177 micron-wide). When Andrew sifts whole wheat flour through this screen, it yields an extraction rate of about 85%, i.e., from 1000 g (35 oz) of grain, he obtains 850 g (30 oz) of flour and 150 g (5 oz) of overs (mostly coarse and medium bran). This sifted flour thus contains the germ and a fair enough proportion of fine brand, as well as a characteristic creamy color and rich aroma due to the carotenoids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While testing the Mockmill, we sifted the whole-wheat flour through a medium, 50 threads per inch (0.0117 inch or 297 microns) screen. This yielded flour with a 72% extraction rate &lt;em&gt;(It is important to note here that the extraction rate of the flour milled with Andrew’s mill and that of the flour milled with the Mockmill could not be adequately compared through our test, because we did not use the same screen gage)&lt;/em&gt;; i.e., from 500 g (18 oz) of wheat grain we got 360 g (13 oz) of sifted flour and 140 g (5 oz) of overs (endosperm remains and coarse bran).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During our test with the Mockmill, the endosperm was not milled thoroughly, which affected the results of the sifting. Andrew advised that it would be better to bake with whole wheat flour in order to benefit from all the grains nutritional potential. However, it is easier to obtain a stronger gluten structure with flour that contains a minimal amount of medium and coarse bran particles, and a higher proportion of endosperm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The finest flour came from setting the mill beyond the marks and running the stand mixer at the fastest speed. The millstones were slightly glazed after our test, because of flour that couldn’t flow out of the mill before it started to heat up—but the stones can be easily cleaned by grinding grain at a coarser level (Mockmill provides cleaning instructions and videos).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/francois-thibeault-033-Andrew-Heyn-mockmill-wp.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Flour milled withh the Mockmill&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Home bakers and artisanal bakers who want to mill their own flour will need to develop new skills in handling flour that is different from “bag” flour on many levels: gluten structure, hydration, aroma, and color. Due to the presence of germ and bran the nutritional value will also be different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finding good grain to mill will be one of the challenges—and possibilities—that miller bakers will have to deal with, because most of the organic grain available in retail stores is still commodity grain grown within a system that values productivity and efficiency over taste and flavor. As the variety of regional wheat keeps expanding, home miller bakers will discover a whole new world of possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only did the Mockmill prove to deliver fresh, aromatic stone-ground flour out of the box, it was also a means for Andrew to show me many of the basics of stone milling. This small piece of equipment possesses a great potential to introduce neophytes, home bakers, and even artisanal bakers to the world of milling-on-the-go. Andrew teaches classes on milling at King Arthur Flour baking school, and considers using the Mockmill to show students basic milling principles and techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the home miller baker, milling your own flour can dramatically change the flavor, aroma, appearance, and taste of your bread. As fresh (“green”) flour is an even more lively ingredient than flour that was oxidized or left to rest for some time, your methods, formulas, and techniques will progressively adapt to this new realm of bread. Surely, there are great opportunities that lie ahead. This may be a turning point in your passion for bread baking!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>François Thibeault</name></author><category term="Craft" /><category term="Andrew Heyn" /><category term="artisan" /><category term="artisanal" /><category term="bakery" /><category term="Elmore Mountain Bread" /><category term="flour" /><category term="Grain" /><category term="Home Milling" /><category term="Issue 21" /><category term="mill" /><category term="milling" /><category term="Mockmill" /><category term="stone mill" /><category term="stone-ground milling" /><category term="test" /><category term="United States" /><category term="Vermont" /><summary type="html">Andrew Heyn—professional craft miller and baker, and stone mills builder—tries out the Mockmill and reports.</summary></entry></feed>